University of Arizona Women's Athletics and Physical Education Papers, 1917-1981 (bulk 1921-1954)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
University of Arizona Women's Athletics and Physical Education Papers, 1917-1981 (bulk 1921-1954)
MS 555
University of Arizona, Department of Physical Education for Women
University of Arizona Women's Athletics and Physical Education Papers (1917-1981) contain documents detailing the history of women’s physical education and athletics at the University. These records were generated primarily by the Department of Physical Education for Women, led by Ina Gittings from 1920-1955. The records include documents, correspondence and photographs pertaining to physical education and varsity intramural sports. National, regional, and university level athletic organizations for college women and administrators are also documented. A small segment of records detail intercollegiate athletic organizations and newspaper clippings of women’s sports competitions under the leadership of athletics administrator, Mary Roby, from 1959-1981.
2.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
none
Biographical Note
In 1920, Ina Gittings joined the faculty at the University and was named the first Director of Physical Education for Women. Prior to 1920, the only college-sponsored activity for women at the University of Arizona was dance. Gittings pioneered the development of the women’s undergraduate physical education program and varsity athletics for women. Both varsity intramural athletics and physical education courses were overseen by Gittings in her role as Director of Physical Education for Women. Under the leadership of Gittings, University of Arizona women were introduced to a variety of intramural sports, including horseback riding, track and field, basketball and archery, among others. Ina Gittings was a lifelong advocate of women’s physical education and athletic competition during a time when women’s athletics was discouraged and perceived as masculinizing women. With her guidance and with the support of University administrators, the University of Arizona saw its intramural athletic program for women increase in size. When Gittings retired in 1955, the University had expanded sponsorship to thirteen varsity sports for female participants.
In 1959, when Mary Pavlich Roby began her career as a Physical Education Instructor, Director of the Women’s Recreation Association, and athletics coach at the University of Arizona, female athletes were participating in only intramural competition. Roby not only served as an athletics administrator at the University of Arizona for 30 years, she helped propel women’s athletics at the University from intramural competition to a well-regarded intercollegiate women’s athletics program.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Department of Physical Education for Women, 1917-1965
Series II: Athletic Organizations and Physical Education Legislation, 1921-1974
Series III: Physical Education Student Papers, 1943-1958
Series IV: Articles, Secretary’s Book, and Clippings, 1921-1981
Scope and Content Note
University of Arizona Women's Athletics and Physical Education Papers (1919-1981) document the history of women’s physical education and athletics at the University of Arizona and women’s athletics in general, in the early to mid-twentieth century. These records were generated primarily by the Department of Physical Education for Women and contain detailed information regarding the history of women’s physical education classes, coursework, and intramural sports from 1920-1955. Materials written by Director of Physical Education for Women, Ina Gittings, and others are also included as well as a history of national physical education legislation. National, regional, and university level athletic organizations for college women and administrators are also documented. A small section of records also detail intercollegiate athletic organizations and clippings from women’s sports under the leadership of Mary Roby, athletics administrator until 1989.
Ina E. Gittings Collection (1890-1985), MS 283
Mary Roby Papers (1926-2012), MS 553
Access Terms
Gittings, Ina E., 1885-1966.
Roby, Mary (Pavlich), 1926-2012.
University of Arizona -- Department of Physical Education for Women.
University of Arizona –- Faculty.
University of Arizona –- Sports.
College Sports – Arizona -- Tucson.
Physical education for women -- Arizona.
Physical Education and Training -- Administration.
Physical Education Teachers –- Arizona.
Sports for Women – Arizona – Tucson.
Articles
Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Department of Physical Education for Women, 1917-1965
  This section is grouped by sport and includes materials from university sponsored high school tournaments, physical education courses and varsity athletics.
  - Annual High School Archery-Badminton Tournament, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gittings Honor Cup – Winners, 1931-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - University of Arizona Bulletin, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Women’s Archery – Intercollegiate Tournaments, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women’s Archery - Publicity, 1933-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women’s Archery - State Tournaments, 1933-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women’s Archery – Correspondence, 1935-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women’s Archery – Women’s Athletic Association Reports, 1936-1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women’s Archery – Club, 1937-1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women’s Archery – Tri-Collegiate Tournaments, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Women’s Archery – Historical Summary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Women’s Basketball – State Tournaments for High School Girls, 1921-1927, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Women’s Basketball – Correspondence, 1922-1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Women’s Basketball – Publicity, 1926-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Women’s Basketball – Women’s Athletic Association, 1926-1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Women’s Basketball – Historical Summary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Women’s Dance – Historical Material, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Women’s Dance – Historical Summary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Women’s Golf – Historical Material, 1935-1950, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Women’s Golf – Publicity, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Women’s Marksmanship – Historical Materials, 1923-1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Women’s Marksmanship – Historical Summary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Women’s Minor Sports – Women’s Athletic Association, 1935-1953 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Women’s Minor Sports – Historical Summary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Women’s Minor Sports – Publicity and Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Women’s Riding – Class Material, 1919, 1921-1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Women’s Riding – Photographs, 1921, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Women’s Riding – Photographs, 1921, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Women’s Riding – Desert Riders, 1921-1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Women’s Riding – Horseshows, 1921-1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Women’s Riding – Correspondence and Articles, 1925-1938, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Women’s Riding – Polo, 1927-1937, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Women’s Riding – Historical Summary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Women’s Softball – Women’s Athletic Association, 1922-1954 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Women’s Softball – Publicity, 1925,1942, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Women’s Softball – Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Women’s Swimming – Historical Materials, 1921-1954 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Women’s Swimming – Photographs, 1931-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Women’s Swimming – Historical Data and Summary, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Women’s Track – Historical Material, 1917-1925, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Women’s Track – Historical Data and Summary, 1922-1923, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Series II: Athletic Organizations and Physical Education Legislation, 1921-1974
  This section contains materials relating to athletic organization for students and administrators at the national, regional, and university level. It also contains a history of national physical education legislation.
  - American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation – Reports and Correspondence, 1922-1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation – Correspondence, 1946-1947, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation – Convention Report, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Arizona Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation – Journal, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Arizona Athletic Federation of College Women – Convention Materials, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Arizona Athletic Federation of College Women – History and Photographs, 1947-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Athletic and Recreation Federation of College Women – Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Athletic and Recreation Federation of College Women – Handbooks, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Athletic Conference of American College Women – Report, 1921, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Athletic Conference of American College Women – Newsletters, 1923-1931 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Athletic Federation of College Women – History (Folder 1 of 2), 1933-1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Athletic Federation of College Women – History (Folder 2 of 2), 1933-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Athletic Federation of College Women – Handbooks, 1933-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Athletic Federation of College Women – Handbook, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Athletic Federation of College Women – Reports, 1946, 1954, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Athletic Federation of College Women – Handbook, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Athletic Federation of College Women – Handbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - College Women’s Sports Association – Platform, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - National Association of Directors of Physical Education for College Women – Correspondence, Newsletters and Programs, 1928-1941 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Association for Physical Education for College Women – Democratic Process Project, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Association for Physical Education for College Women – Democratic Process Supplement, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Women’s Athletic Association – History, 1930-1932, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Women’s Recreation Association – Newsletters, 1962-1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Women’s Weekend and Social Recreation Programs – Correspondence, 1945, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Legislation: HR 10606 National Physical Education Bill -Correspondence and Bill Document, 1927-1933, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Physical Education Student Papers, 1943-1958
  This series contains student papers written to fulfill course requirements for Ina Gittings, Director of Physical Education. It also contains information on the Physical Education major in the early 1950’s.
  - Physical Education Student Papers (Folder 1 of 2), 1943-1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Physical Education Student Papers (Folder 2 of 2), 1943-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Women’s Physical Education Major – Newsletter, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Articles, Secretary’s Book, and Newspaper Clippings, 1921-1981
  This series is comprised of clippings and articles. Clippings are from the Women’s Athletic Association and include intramural and intercollegiate athletics. This series also contains articles written by University faculty and students.
  - Women’s Athletic Association – Clippings, circa 1921-1924 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Women’s Athletic Association – Secretary’s Book, circa 1921-1923 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics Cuts – Clippings, circa 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Women’s Athletics - Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Physical Education Programs and Public Relations - Articles, 1961, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correlation of Mental and Physical Traits in University of Arizona Freshmen Women – Condensed Thesis by Ina Gittings, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Why Cramp Competition?– Article by Ina Gittings, 1931, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - A Study of the Scholarship of Participants and Non-Participants in the Extra-Curricular Program as Set Up by the Department of Physical Education for Women, University of Arizona- Thesis by Mildred Samuelson, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Some Health Problems of College Women– Article by Eleanor Metheny, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The New Menace – Article by Ina Gittings, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Why I Make Susie Run Article by Pat Anderson, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)